Guide to the Alton Crane Melville family home movies 1940-1968
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
- White and Melville, Neffs Canyon, Millcreek Canyon, El Sennito tank 4, Las Vegas, Los Angeles, Amelia, 1952-1953; 8mm film (Reel 43)
  Footage of the Melville family's 1952 hike in Neffs Canyon as well as their trips to Las Vegas, and Los Angeles. In Las Vegas, they watch speed boat races and in Los Angeles, they tour the city. This film also contains images of the White and Melville water well and of men working on an irrigation system in the canyon during the winter.
- Intermountain Giant Slalom,National Juniors at Brighton, jumping at Alta, Harriman Cup at Sun Valley, 1953 February; 8mm film (Reel 44)
  This film contains footage of Marvin Melville racing in several races. These races include the Intermountain Giant Slalom race, the National Juniors race held at Brighton, the Landes Jumping competition at Alta, and the Harriman Cup in Sun Valley Idaho.
- Skiing, State Fair, Neffs Cave, Snow Cup at Brighton, Eccles Cup at Snow Basin, 1953-1954; 8mm film (Reel 45)
  The Melville family hiking up Neffs Canyon to Neffs Cave, which is one of the deepest caves in Utah. Marvin racing in the January Snow Cup held at Brighton, and in the Eccles Cup held at Snow Basin. Along with the footage of Marvin competing in these two races is footage of Marvin and Marie free skiing together.
- Skiing: Brighton to Homestead, Harriman Cup, Intermountain Giant Slolm, costume race, 1953-1954; 8mm film (Reel 46)
  Marvin Melville competing in the eleventh annual Harriman Cup, the Intermountain Giant Slalom race, and in a costume race. This reel also contains footage of the Melville family skiing from Brighton to The Homestead. The footage of the Harriman Cup includes a list of tentative starting times for the Slalom and Giant Slalom events, images of the crowd cheering, and of the racers getting ready and skiing the course. The Harriman Cup was held in Sun Valley Idaho on March 20-21, 1954. The footage from the Intermountain Giant Slalom race includes images of the racers getting ready, the racers in the course, and the crowd cheering. This race was held at Brighton in March 1954. The Costume Race was also held at Brighton but was in May of 1954. The footage from this race consists of a view of the resort from above and images of the racers in costume skiing the course. The footage of the Melville family skiing from Brighton to the Homestead includes images of the family hiking to the top of the mountain then skiing down it's ridgeline and through some trees.
- Jackson Hole, Whites, Knight, Little Cottonwood, Whites up Mineral Fork, 1954; 8mm film (Reel 47)
  The Melville's trip to Jackson Hole with the White family A day of hiking in Little Cottonwood Canyon The Melville and White families up Mineral Fork. The footage of their trip to Jackson Hole includes images of the children playing, the fathers fishing, and the mothers knitting. There are also images of the surrounding scenery. The footage from the day spent up Little Cottonwood Canyon includes scenic images as well as images of the family hiking. The footage of the White and Melville families up Mineral fork consists of scenic images.
- Ski pictures: College Jump (Alf Engen and Marvin), Snow Cup at Alta, Intermountain Junior Races in Ogden (Marie), Hariman Cup in Sun Valley, 1954-1955; 8mm film (Reel 48)
  Marvin training with Alf Engen at the College Jump and competing in the Snow Cup at Alta and in the Harriman Cup in Sun Valley. The footage of the races includes images of the racers getting ready and skiing the course. This film also contains footage of Marie competing in the International Junior races at Snow Basin.
- Yosemite, Las Vegas Parade, Dimple Dell Farm, 1955 May-June; 8mm film (Reel 49)
  The Melville's trips to Yosemite National Park, Las Vegas, and Dimple Dell: The footage from Yosemite includes a view of a waterfall, and the scenic view from Glacier Point and Fresno. The footage from Las Vegas is of a street parade. The footage from Dimple Dell is of farmland being cleared of shrubbery and the like.
- Dimple Dell well, 1955 July; 8mm film (Reel 50)
  Several men working on an irrigation system for a farm in Dimple Dell. The men also preform well tests.
- Nevada, California, Pineview, July 4th, Fork Barker Ranch, Montana, wedding, 1955-1957; 16mm film (Reel 51)
  Various trips that the Melville family went on from 1955-1957: The footage from Nevada contains images of the Melville family swimming in a pool at a Hotel. The footage from California contains images of the family swimming in the ocean, going to Disney Land and to the Marine Park. The footage from Pineview contains images of the Melville family driving jeeps off road. The footage from Montana contains images of the family visiting Fork Barker Ranch, where they feed fawns from a bottle, go horseback riding, and canoeing on a pond. The film ends with footage of a wedding and images from before and after the ceremony. There are images of the guests mingling outdoors and of the bride, groom, bride's maids and men of honor all in a line.
- Winter Olympics, Alta, 1956; 16mm film (Reel 52)
  The 1956 Winter Olympics where hosted by Cortina d'Ampezzo Italy. The featured footage of the Winter Olympics consists of the flag carrying ceremony, the opening ceremony, the torch lighting ceremony, and the various events that the Melville family attended while in Italy. These events include bobsledding, hockey, nordic skiing, giant slalom, figure skating, and downhill. This film also includes footage of the Melville family skiing at Alta
- Dozer, Big Cottonwood Canyon, 1957; 8mm film (Reel 53)
  Construction of the road going up Big Cottonwood Canyon.
- Skiing at Badgastein, 1957; 16mm film Poor color quality (Reel 54)
  Marvin Melville training for giant slalom in Badgastein, Austria in the Tauern Mountain Range.
- Europe, 1957; 16mm film (Reel 55)
  Marvin Melville's trip to Europe where he races in both slalom and giant slalom events. At the end of this film, there is a close up of the local newspaper.
- Nevada mine, 1957 November; 8mm film (Reel 56)
  Two men skiing while a dog plays in the snow. Images of the Nevada mines.
- Dozer ABOC, 1957; 8mm film (Reel 57)
  A bulldozer cleraing land.
- European trip, Alta Snow Cup, A.C Melville, Salt Lake City, 1958; 16mm film (Reel 58)
  The Melville Family's trip to Europe, where Marvin competes in various ski races, as well as footage of Marvin racing in the Alta Snow Cup in Salt Lake City, Utah: The footage from Europe contains images of the family arriving in Amsterdam where they then board a ferry and then get back onto a plane. They arrive in Germany where they go sight seeing. Later they arrive at the Munche Ski Resort where Marvin races in a slalom, giant slalom, and downhill race. Marvin's race number is 23. The next scenes from Europe are of the Melville family walking the streets of Zurich, Switzerland, Naples, Italy, and Nice, France. In Nice, the family attends a street parade, and then travels to Paris to visits the Louvre Museum. In Stockholm, Sweden, the family attends another street parade, and visit Mount Melville. The Alta Snow Cup that Marvin competes in is composed of a slalom race under the FIS Alpine heading.
- Home, Zeus Landes, Snow Cup at Ecker Hill, Steamboat, Olympic Tryouts, Squaw Valley, Sun Valley, Aspen, 1958-1959; 16mm film (Reel 59)
  Footage of an older couple riding a tandem bicycle followed by footage of the Melville family playing with two dogs. This film also contains footage of Marvin Melville competing in various races. These races include the Home Zeus Landes Long Jumping competition, the Snow Cup on Ecker Hill in Steamboat Colorado, the 1959 North American Championships, the Harriman Cup in Sun Valley, and a slalom race in Aspen.
- Marti, Easter, Marvin's graduation, Yellowstone, Glacier National Park, Marie goes to Europe, airport, Whites on Yellowstone Lake, bicycles, Cody, Marti, snow, 1959-1960; 16mm film (Reel 60)
  The Melville family at home and on various trips that the Melvilles went on from 1959-1960. These trips include a trip to Yellowstone National Park where the family visits the Old Faithful Geyser and then take a tour through Glacier National Park. The Melville family returns to Yellowstone National Park with the White family. Together they go boating, feed the birds, and see a brown bear eating. Marie Melville's boards the airplane for her trip to Europe. The footage of the Melville family includes footage of their family Easter celebration, of Marti Melville as a baby, of Marvin's Graduation from the University of Utah, and of the family riding their bicycles.
- University of Utah dry land training, Marvin: slalom, NCAA downhill, NCAA jumping, 1959-1963; 16mm film (Reel 61)
  Marvin Melville training and competing in various ski events. The beginning of the film contains footage of the University of Utah's ski team dry land training followed by footage of Marvin training for slalom in December of 1959. The races that Marvin competes in are the NCAA downhill event, held in February of 1961, and the NCAA Jumping event in 1963.
- Mill D, south fork of Big Cottonwood Canyon, Frank Yanchar, Vare Frantz Road To Venus, 94 South, well test 14, Belnap Well test, White Pine Little Cottonwood Creek dam, Peruvian Road construction, Dam Mert Wensens, Albion Basin, 1959-1963; 16mm film (Reel 62)
  Various construction sites and well testing: The first construction site seen is in the South Fork of Big Cottonwood Canyon and the second site is the road construction to the Peruvian in Little Cottonwood Canyon. The well testing is done at the Cardiff Fork where some mining is also seen. This film also contains scenic views from White Pine and Albion Basin.
- Winter Olympics, Squaw Valley, 1960; 16mm film (Reel 63)
  The 1960 Winter Olympics held in Squaw Valley, California. Having competed in the 1956 Winter Olympics in Cortina d'Ampezzo, and for the National Federation of Skiing Team in 1958 in Badgastein Austria, Marvin competes in his last international race before moving on to coaching ski teams. The event that he competed in was downhill racing. This film begins with footage of the Melville family packing their camper and driving to California on the ninth of February 1960. The first Olympic event that the family sees is figure skating. The second event that is shown is the downhill race, which was held on February 14. After the race, the Melville family and a few friends go to the Squaw Valley Lodge for lunch. During lunch, Mrs. Hanna's ski are stolen. On February 17 the Melville family attends another downhill race featuring a disabled skier named Lowell Thomas. After this, they attend an Olympic Ceremony followed by the ladies downhill, and the men's giant slalom events. On February 20 there is yet another downhill event which is filmed with greater detail than the first two. On February 24 the Melville family attends an ice hockey event, a cross-country skiing event, and the eighty-meter jumping event. The last events that the Melville family attended were speed skating, pairs figure skating, and ladies slalom ski racing.
- Bicycle State Championships, Liberty Park, trip to Key West, 1961; 16mm film (Reel 64)
  Footage of the Mountain States Cycling Scene Race Awards and of the Melville family's trips to Key West, Florida, Miami and the Everglades. In Key West, the family goes to the Marine Studios where they see Dolphins, Ducks, Sea Turttles, and other marine life. In Miami, they float a river where they see a man wrestle an alligator, and then they take a train tour. In the Everglades, the Melville family goes on a boat trip.
- County water system, well at 275 East 30 South, 1961 January; 16mm film (Reel 65)
  Salt Lake County's water tanks from above. Images if several real estate signs, possibly in consideration for developing future water tanks on. Several men working on a well located at 275 East and 300 South. Several scenes with images of records filling the entire frame. The last image is of a newspaper headline that reads Residents Face 3d Waterless Days.
- Training school, Aspen, Sun Valley, 1961-1962; 16mm film (Reel 66)
  This film was directed by Marvin Melville, Dick Street, Bill Spencer, and Al Hansen and contains footage of the high school ski team training for Slalom and Giant Slalom in addition to dry land training. The dry land training consists of running, sprinting, sit-ups, push-ups, climbing stairs, summersaults and climbing a rope.
- Christmas, Marti & Shari, Easter, Bob & Marie's graduation, Dick Street wedding, Cloud Rim Road on Rainbow, Little Cottonwood, Mindy & Mel, Easter, Verna & ladies, July 4th parade, girls & dog, Sorensens Indians, girls on skis, 1961-1963; 16mm film (Reel 67)
  The Melville family celebrating various holidays as well as footage of the Melville family with various friends. The holidays celebrated in this film include Christmas 1961, Easter 1962 and 1963, and the 4th of July, which was hosted by the Sorensen family. This film also contains footage of Marie's graduation from the University of Utah on June 11, 1962 and footage of Dick Street's wedding.
- Brighton races, 1963 January; 16mm film (Reel 68)
  Marvin Melville competing in the 1963 January Juniors Cup. The event featured in this footage is a giant slalom race.
- Dry land, cross country skiing, 1964; 8mm film (Reel 69)
  Marvin Melville's dry land training exercises and Marvin Melville cross-country skiing. The exercises included in the dry land training are soccer and water exercises.
- December, 1965; 16mm film (Reel 70)
  The Melville family's Christmas celebration: gathering with the extended family, decorating the Christmas tree, opening presents.
- Draper well, 1965; 16mm film (Reel 71)
  Several men working on a water well in Draper, Utah.
- Slalom training session, Sun Valley Competition, 1965-1966; 8mm film (Reel 72)
  Marvin Melville training for slalom skiing and competing in various races. These races include the Solitude Cup held on March 15 1965, the NCAA Downhill Competition held at Crystal Mountain on March 27, 1956, the Nationals slalom and giant slalom events held on April 2, 1965 and the 1966 Sun Valley Competition.
- Landes jumping, 1965 December 10; 1966 December; 8mm film (Reel 73)
  This film contains footage of Marvin Melville long jumping on the Landes Jump.
- Finlaysen ranch, snowmobiling trip in Yellowstone, 1965 July; 1968 March; 8mm film (Reel 74)
  The Melville family's trips to the Finlaysen Ranch and to Yellowstone National Park: The footage of the ranch includes several shots of the animals, the land, the Finlaysen's home, and of the tractor in the fields. The footage of their snowmobiling trip to Yellowstone National Park includes several shots of the family's picnic at Madison Junction and of various surrounding bison.